{"tossups": [{"question": "This event ended when acting governor Thomas Hutchison promised a fair investigation into this event if the crowd watching the event dispersed. This event is depicted in a famous engraving by Paul Revere. John Adams defended eight soldiers involved in this event that led to the death of a black dockworker named Crispus Attucks. For ten points, name this 1770 event in which British soldiers fired on a crowd, killing five unarmed citizens in the capital of Massachusetts.", "answer": "<b> Boston Massacre</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In front of this structure while standing in a bucket crane, David Hasselhoff performed his hit song\u201cLooking for Freedom\u201d before thousands of activists in 1989. Peter Fechter was shot and killed along the\u201cdeath strip\u201d of this structure by guards on one side. A country on one side of this structure referred to it as the Anti-Fascist Protection Rampart. For ten points, name this structure which Ronald Reagan asked Mikhail Gorbachev to tear down while it still divided a German city.", "answer": "<b> Berlin Wall</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Located on the Arno, six miles from the Ligurian Sea, this city was once considered the main port in Tuscany and is noted for its inclined campanile, or \u201cleaning tower.\u201d For ten points, name this Italian city.", "answer": "<b> Pisa</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man built a line of fortifications around Alesia to defeat Vercingetorix and demanded that his pirate captors ransom him for a higher sum of money. The phrase \u201cthe die is cast\u201d was uttered by this lover of Cleopatra before he crossed the Rubicon. This man\u2019s assumption of extraordinary powers was opposed by Cassius and Brutus. For ten points, name this member of the First Triumvirate and Roman dictator who was assassinated on the Ides of March.", "answer": "Gaius<b> Julius Caesar</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Jean Gerson helped resolve a crisis in this organization by rejecting two candidates to lead it, while Emperor John VIII joined the Council of Ferrara-Florence to seek the aid of this organization. This organization was based out of Avignon with the support of Philip IV, but it moved back to its original home after the Council of Constance. This organization split with its Eastern counterpart in 1054 after an excommunication from the Ecumenical Patriarch. For ten points, name this organization headed by the Pope in Rome.", "answer": "Roman<b> Catholic Church</b> (prompt on Vatican, See of Rome, or Holy See)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A 13-Point Program was issued by people of this nationality who founded the Chicago-based Young Lords. At the Blair House, two people of this nationality carried out a failed assassination attempt on Harry Truman. The citizenship rights for people of this nationality were granted in the Jones-Shafroth Act. By 1950, over 60,000 of these people lived in an area close to 110th Street in New York that became known as Spanish Harlem. For ten points, what is this nationality given to people from an American island Commonwealth in the Caribbean.", "answer": "<b> Puerto Rican</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "One of these events was witnessed by John Joseph Henry while imprisoned on the HMS<em> Pearl</em> in New York Harbor in 1776. A shed on DeKoven Street was supposedly the first building destroyed in an 1871 event of this type, which allegedly began when Mrs. O\u2019Leary\u2019s cow overturned a lantern. In 2020, the most damaging event of this type in U.S. history destroyed more than 4.4 million acres. For ten points, name these events, one of which caused much of Chicago to burn.", "answer": "Wild<b>fire</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In this city, a lawyer named Theodore Landsmark was attacked with an American flag in a Pulitzer Prize-winning photo titled<em> The Soiling of Old Glory</em>. ROAR was an organization created in response to the 1974 desegregation of schools in this city. During a 1969 Moratorium to End the War in Vietnam, over 100 thousand protestors gathered in this city\u2019s namesake Common. Occupy protests in this city were covered by reporters for its<em> Globe</em> newspaper. For ten points, name this capital of Massachusetts.", "answer": "<b> Boston</b>, Massachusetts", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was recognized in the Treaty of Le Goulet, though he later lost the battle of Bouvines to its other signatory, Philip Augustus. This man refused to recognize Stephen Langton as Archbishop of Canterbury, leading Innocent III to excommunicate this man in 1209. After he was cornered at Runnymede by disgruntled nobles, this man was forced to sign a document that outlined principles such as \u201chabeas corpus.\u201d For ten points, name this English king who signed the Magna Carta in 1215.", "answer": "<b> John</b> (accept<b> John</b> Lackland)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The Missouri Bootheel was the main area affected by one of these events that began at 2 A.M. on December 16, 1811. That event of this type was interpreted by some Native Americans as a sign that they should support Tecumseh\u2019s War. Occurring in the New Madrid [MAD-rid], zone that event was the most powerful event of this type east of the Rocky Mountains. For ten points, name these seismic events.", "answer": "<b> Earthquake</b>s", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man\u2019s last words noted that a rooster was owed to Asclepius, after this man\u2019s prior refusal to save himself served as the basis for the dialogue \u201cCrito.\u201d This man, who described himself as a \u201cgadfly,\u201dwas depicted by Jacques-Louis David drinking hemlock shortly after he faced trial for corrupting the youth of Athens. For ten points, name this philosopher, the teacher of Plato, who quoted this man in his <em>Apology</em> saying, \u201cthe unexamined life is not worth living.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Socrates</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "The original \u201cYankee Doodle\u201d song makes reference to this figure, whose outfit was likely inspired by that of Brother Jonathan. Thomas Nast was the first to draw cartoons of this allegorical figure whom James Montgomery Flagg depicted in war recruiting posters saying \u201cI want you.\u201d For ten points, name this top hat-wearing figure who allegorically represents the United States.", "answer": "<b> Uncle Sam</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "In one of this actor\u2019s films, Harlen Maguire is tasked with assassinating this actor\u2019s character, Michael Sullivan, an Irish mobster in Depression-era Illinois. In another film, this man fires a pistol repeatedly at an approaching tank when the tank is suddenly bombed from above. This actor in the 2002 film<em> Road to</em> <em>Perdition</em>, commands the 2nd Ranger Battalion in a film which opens with the landing at Normandy. In that film, this man play Captain John Miller, whose men are tasked with finding a missing paratrooper. For ten points, name this actor who starred in<em> Saving Private Ryan</em>.", "answer": "Tom<b> Hanks</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s reign, 24 carriage loads of Jewish manuscripts were burned after his court presided over a disputation known as the \u201cTrial of the Talmud.\u201d This man dispatched William of Rubruck to the Golden Horde in an attempt to garner support. Though this son of Blanche of Castile captured Damietta, he was defeated at Al Mansurah shortly afterward by the Mamelukes. This man\u2019s subsequent leadership of the Eighth Crusade ended when he died of dysentery in 1270. For ten points, name this man, the only king of France canonized by the Catholic church.", "answer": "<b> Louis IX</b> (accept<b> Saint Louis</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This seven-word phrase ended a speech that prompted Edward Carrington to ask to be buried on the spot. This phrase appeared in a speech whose speaker claims to have \u201cbut one</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>lamp by which my feet are guided; and that is the lamp of experience.\u201d This phrase\u2019s</b> <b>first published appearance was in a biography of its Virginia-born speaker by William Wirt. Its orator said this phrase in a speech addressed to Peyton Randolph during a (*) </b> 1775 convention held in Williamsburg. For ten points, name this famous exclamation delivered by Patrick Henry.", "answer": "\u201c<b>Give me liberty, or give me death!</b>\u201d", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Alex Kershaw\u2019s book</b><em><b> The Bedford Boys</b></em><b> chronicled the story of Company A of the 116th Infantry, which suffered heavy losses during this battle. Operation Fortitude South sought to convince the defenders that George Patton\u2019s First United States Army Group would</b> <b>target (+)</b> <b>Pas-de-Calais instead of the objective of this operation. James Rudder\u2019s Army</b> <b>Pas-de-Calais instead of the objective of this operation. James Rudder\u2019s Army</b> <b>Rangers suffered heavy losses while storming the (*)</b> <b>Rangers suffered heavy losses while storming the (*)</b> cliffs of Pointe-du-Hoc during this battle. Five beachheads were established at Sword, Gold, Juno, Utah, and Omaha during this battle. For ten points, name this June 6, 1944 Allied invasion of Normandy.", "answer": "<b> D-Day</b> (accept<b> Operation Overlord</b>, accept<b> Battle of Normandy</b> before it is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>This event occurred on the same day that Annie Leibovitz took a photo of its central figure curled up naked next to his clothed wife. The perpetrator of this action was caught</b> <b>holding a copy of</b><em><b> The Catcher in the Rye</b></em><b>. The (+)</b> <b>victim was returning to the Dakota</b> <b>apartment complex from the Record Plant Studio. The song \u201cAll My Loving\u201d came over emergency room speakers at a hospital just as the victim of this event died. A portion of Central Park called (*)</b> Strawberry Fields was created after this event, which was carried out by Mark Chapman. Yoko Ono became a widow after, for ten points, what event that resulted in the death of a Beatle?", "answer": "<b> Murder</b> of John<b> Lennon</b> (accept assassination or other equivalents to murder of John <b>Lennon</b>) (4) <b>The second of these conflicts featured Barcids fighting on three fronts, including two</b> <b>The second of these conflicts featured Barcids fighting on three fronts, including two</b> <b>sons of Hamilcar. The loser of the third of these conflicts was raided by (+)</b> <b>sons of Hamilcar. The loser of the third of these conflicts was raided by (+)</b> <b>Numidians</b> <b>and fell after a three-year siege under Scipio Aemilianus. The second of these conflicts was a sixteen year long campaign that ended at the Battle of Zama. Cato the Elder ended every</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man may have devised a ship to collapse on itself in an attempt to assassinate his mother. This man sent Corbulo to the East after the Parthians attempted to place Tiridates on the throne of Armenia, while his general (+) Suetonius was responsible for suppressing the revolt of Boudicca. This man poisoned Britannicus to secure power, though he himself (*)</b> committed suicide, beginning the Year of the Four Emperors. For ten points, name this emperor who was said to have fiddled as Rome burned.", "answer": "<b> Nero</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "Legends claim that</b> <b>an Ethiopian named Kaldi discovered the major (+)</b> <b>effects of this good after his goats</b> <b>consumed it. A Red Sea port in Yemen that extensively traded this good lends its name to one of its most common types today. Sufis allegedly used this substance while performing rituals that required them to (*) </b> stay awake for long periods. For ten points, name this substance whose variations include Ristretto, Turkish, and Cappuccino.", "answer": "<b> Coffee</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b>During a battle for this city, sniper fire killed General Robert Ross, who turned command over to Arthur Brooke moments before dying. The Battle of North Point was fought in this city, and a naval attack on this city (+) inspired a lawyer who had negotiated the release of William Beanes to write a poem that was later set to the (*)</b> tune of \u201cTo Anacreon in Heaven.\u201dFor ten points, name this Maryland city that was defended by Fort McHenry in the War or 1812, whose bombing inspired the writing of \u201cThe Star Spangled Banner.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Baltimore</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "5 million intellectuals in mass graves known as (*)</b> Killing Fields. For ten points, name this political party led by Pol Pot which perpetrated the 1970s genocide in Cambodia.", "answer": "<b> Khmer Rouge</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}